Guide to the Claire Holt papers, 1927-1970.
Holt, Claire papers
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Claire Holt papers, 1927-1970.
14-27-2648
Holt, Claire.
6.8 cubic ft.
Correspondence, Photographs, Research Materials
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Collection consists of slides, correspondence, and research materials of Claire Holt.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Journalist.
Claire Holt was born in Riga, Latvia in 1901. She served as a reporter for the The New York World, publishing dance reviews. She traveled to Indonesia in 1930, where she studied dance, working with the anthropologist Willem Stutterheim and then assisting the Swedish dance archivist and patron Rolf de Mare with his photo and film documentation of Indonesian dance. She returned to the U.S. and served as a research assistant to Margaret Mead, as a research analyst for the Office of Strategic Services, and as a foreign affairs specialist for the State Department. She then came to Cornell University, where in 1962, she helped found the Modern Indonesia Project.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Collection consists of slides of Indonesia created for the Cornell Indonesian Arts Project. Subjects include art, architecture, ceremonies, landscapes, painting, people, sculpture, textiles, and theater. Collection also includes research materials, typescript notes about a trip to Indonesia in 1955-1956, index cards relating to Holt's work and travel in Indonesia, and materials from the dedication of the Claire Holt Memorial Collection Inauguration Ceremony at Lembaga, August 6, 1970.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Holt, Claire.; Cornell University. Indonesian Arts Project.; Cornell University. Southeast Asia Program.
Subjects:
Art, Indonesian.; Arts, Indonesian.; Painting, Indonesian.; Sculpture, Indonesian.; Dancing -- Indonesia.; Theater -- Indonesia.
Places:
Indonesia -- Description and travel -- Views.
Form and Genre Terms:
Color slides.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
RELATED MATERIALS
See digital versions of some of this material here: http://resolver.library.cornell.edu/misc/5597787.
The Claire Holt Collection of Indonesian Dance and Related Arts is located in the Dance Division of the New York Public Library.
NOTES
See also: Claire Holt Papers digital collection (NX580.A1 C55 2002), which consists of digitized slides from this collection.
SERIES LIST
Series I. Visual Materials
Series II. Correspondence
Subseries IIa. Individuals
Subseries IIb. Groups and Organizations
Series III. Research Materials
Series IV. Lectures and Writings
Series V. Cornell Indonesian Arts Program
Series VI. Claire Holt Memorial Collection
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I. Visual Materials
  See digital versions of some of this material here: http://resolver.library.cornell.edu/misc/5597787.
  - Slides S1-S280 (Box 1)
  - Slides S281-S468 (Box 2)
  - Slides S469-S693 (Box 3)
  - Slides S684-S871 (Box 4)
  - Slides S872-S1101 (Box 5)
  - Slides S1102-SA125 (Box 6)
  - Slides SA126-SD111 (Box 7)
  - Slides SD112-SD209 (Box 8)
  - Travel notebooks with labelled photographs, 1955-1956 (Box 9)
  - Catalog of Claire Holt's slides (Box 13, Folder 37)
  - Four miscellaneous photographs (Box 13, Folder 42)
  - Black and white negatives (Box 18)
  - CDs- digitized slides (Box 20)
  - CDs- digitized slides (Box 21)
- Series II. Correspondence
  - Subseries IIa. Individuals
    - Miscellaneous, Boston, 1936-1939 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Miscellaneous, March-August 1946 (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence, 1948-1952 (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - Miscellaneous, 1946-1953 (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - U.S. miscellaneous, 1957-1958 (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - Miscellaneous individual and regional, 1956-1967 (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - Affandi visit and exhibition, 1962 (Box 10, Folder 8)
    - Bagong and Wisnu, narration and programs, 1957-1958 (Box 10, Folder 9)
    - Bandung "Seni Rupa", miscellaneous, 1956-1969 (Box 10, Folder 10)
    - Biddle, George, 1929 (Box 10, Folder 11)
    - Budiardjo, Ali and Mill. Djakarta, 1955-1961 (Box 10, Folder 12)
    - Dr. Cense, regarding dance quest, 1939-1940 (Box 10, Folder 13)
    - de Madre, Rolf. Sumatra, 1952-1963 (Box 10, Folder 14)
    - Fahs, Charles. Rockefeller Foundation, 1950-1959 (Box 10, Folder 15)
    - Hadian, Sukarno Joguja, 1956-1963 (Box 10, Folder 16)
    - Hasan, Djaafar, November 1962 (Box 10, Folder 17)
    - Heine-Geldern, Robert. Lectures and visit, sea program, 1962 (Box 10, Folder 18)
    - Hoykaas, Chris. London, 1968-1969 (Box 10, Folder 19)
    - Hsii, C.M.. Djakarta, 1963-1968 (Box 10, Folder 20)
    - Indonesian visitors to USA, Ithaca, 1964-1966 (Box 10, Folder 21)
    - Kats, Ivan, 1962-1970 (Box 10, Folder 22)
    - Kats, Ivan. "Tiger Tiger" translation, March 1966 (Box 10, Folder 23)
    - Keuning, J. Regarding Toba Batick article, 1958 (Box 10, Folder 24)
    - Kusnadi, Jogjukarta, 1956-1959 (Box 10, Folder 25)
    - Kusnadi's visit, 1964 (Box 10, Folder 26)
    - Kussudiardjo, Bagong. Includes three photographs, 1958-1959 (Box 10, Folder 27)
    - Kusumobroto, Sri, 1968-1969 (Box 10, Folder 28)
    - Lomax, Alan, 1967-1969 (Box 10, Folder 29)
    - Lombard, Denys, 1970 (Box 10, Folder 30)
    - Mangkeonagoro VII, 1932-1941 (Box 10, Folder 31)
    - McCray, Porter P., 1964-1969 (Box 10, Folder 32)
    - Moertono, Soemarsaid, 1967-1969 (Box 10, Folder 33)
    - Muchtar, But. Bangdung, 1962-1970 (Box 10, Folder 34)
    - Noom, Yunaidharma visit, 1967 (Box 10, Folder 35)
    - Papadimitriou, Alexis, 1970 (Box 10, Folder 36)
    - Parker, Harrison. Djakarta, 1960-1968 (Box 10, Folder 37)
    - Raffel, Burton. Regarding Indonesian poetry, 1960-1967 (Box 10, Folder 38)
    - Resink, GJ. Djakarta-Amsterdam, 1955-1970 (Box 10, Folder 39)
    - Resink, Th.. Translations for Indonesia, 1967-1968 (Box 10, Folder 40)
    - Rhodius, Hans. Geneva-Amsterdam, 1939-1969 (Box 10, Folder 41)
    - Said, Jusuf. Medan, Sumatra, 1956-1958 (Box 10, Folder 42)
    - Scott, AC, 1969 (Box 10, Folder 43)
    - Smith, Datus Jr. (JDR 3rd fund), 1954-1970 (Box 10, Folder 44)
    - Soemardjan, Selo. Djakarta, 1964-1966 (Box 10, Folder 45)
    - Solo miscellaneous, 1956-1957 (Box 10, Folder 46)
    - Stutterheim (Box 10, Folder 47)
    - Receipts and telegrams to Stutterheim, 1927-1940 (Box 10, Folder 48)
    - Poems by Holt and Stutterheim. Includes three miscellaneous photographs, 1929-1930 (Box 10, Folder 49)
    - Stutterheim, 1931-1939 (Box 10, Folder 50)
    - Stutterheim, January-June 1932 (Box 10, Folder 51)
    - Stutterheim, July-December 1932 (Box 10, Folder 52)
    - Stutterheim, 1933 (Box 10, Folder 53)
    - Stutterheim, 1937-1938 (Box 10, Folder 54)
    - Stutterheim, 1939-1941 (Box 10, Folder 55)
    - Sudjatmoko, 1955-1969 (Box 10, Folder 56)
    - Surabaya miscellaneous, 1955-1956 (Box 10, Folder 57)
    - Tirtaamidjaja, Ivan (dance project), 1965 (Box 10, Folder 58)
    - Soedarsono, Asti, 1966-1969 (Box 10, Folder 59)
    - Trisno, Sumardjo. Djakarta, 1958-1959 (Box 10, Folder 60)
    - Underwood, Dixon F., 1968-1970 (Box 10, Folder 61)
    - Van der Veur, Paul. Ohio University, 1970 (Box 10, Folder 62)
    - Van Erp, Theo and Betsy, 1939-1941 (Box 10, Folder 63)
    - Van Erp, John, 1968 (Box 10, Folder 64)
    - Van Lohuizen, Dr. Leeuw, Dr. Johanna E., 1965-1969 (Box 10, Folder 65)
    - Wisnuwardana, Jogjakarta, 1958-1959 (Box 10, Folder 66)
    - Yudhokusumo, Kartono and his father, 1957 (Box 10, Folder 67)
  - Subseries IIb. Groups and organizations
    - Art Association, patrons etc., 1939-1940 (Box 10, Folder 68)
    - Asian associations, 1944-1946 (Box 10, Folder 69)
    - Asian associations, 1945-1948 (Box 10, Folder 70)
    - Asian associations, March-May 1948 (Box 10, Folder 71)
    - Asian associations, May-June 1948 (Box 10, Folder 72)
    - The Asia Society, 1957-1959 (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - The Asia Society: Sherbet, Landry and Sorensen, Wendy, 1960-1967 (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - The Asia Society notes, 1963-1965 (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - Asia Society Indonesia Council, Committee on Archaeology and Art History. Notes and Correspondence, 1964-1965 (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - The Asia Society: Wendy S. Fund, 1966-1969 (Box 11, Folder 6)
    - The Asia Society notes and correspondence, 1966-1969 (Box 11, Folder 7)
    - The Asia Society tour, Jan.-Feb. 1969 (Box 11, Folder 8)
    - Bali miscellaneou, 1956-1958 (Box 11, Folder 9)
    - Balinese cloth painting, with photographs and negatives, 1967 (Box 11, Folder 10)
    - Translation for Congress for cultural freedom, 1960-1965 (Box 11, Folder 11)
    - Translation for Congress for Cultural Freedom, 1961-1963 (Box 11, Folder 12)
    - Intra-Cornell, 1954-1970 (Box 11, Folder 13)
    - Cornell Southeast Asia Program, 1959-1968 (Box 11, Folder 14)
    - Cornell- But Muchtar and Srihai art exhibition, White Museum, 1961 (Box 11, Folder 15)
    - Cornell public relations, 1957-1958 (Box 11, Folder 16)
    - Cornell University Press and Public Relations, 1968 (Box 11, Folder 17)
    - Djakarta miscellaneous, 1959-1969 (Box 11, Folder 18)
    - East Asia Institute, April-July 1946 (Box 11, Folder 19)
    - East Asia Institute, September-October 1946 (Box 11, Folder 20)
    - East Asia Institute, October-November 1946 (Box 11, Folder 21)
    - East Indies Institute of America, March-June 1944 (Box 11, Folder 22)
    - East Indies Institute of America, 1944-1945 (Box 11, Folder 23)
    - East Indies Institute of America, 1944-1945 (Box 11, Folder 24)
    - Holland, 1946-1953 (Box 11, Folder 25)
    - Contracts to and from Indonesia, 1955-1957 (Box 11, Folder 26)
    - Indonesia, 1946-1953 (Box 11, Folder 26A)
    - Indonesia, Embassy and Consulate General, 1955-1970 (Box 11, Folder 27)
    - Jogujakarta, 1956-1967 (Box 11, Folder 28)
    - Kraton, Mosque, Pendopo, 1955 (Box 11, Folder 29)
    - Lecture engagements, 1936-1948 (Box 11, Folder 30)
    - National Archaeological Institute, 1968-1969 (Box 11, Folder 31)
    - Professional, 1957-1965 (Box 11, Folder 32)
    - Professional, 1961-1963 (Box 11, Folder 33)
    - Professional, 1962-1964 (Box 11, Folder 34)
    - Professional, includes some photographs, 1965-1968 (Box 11, Folder 35)
    - Professional, 1967-1968 (Box 11, Folder 36)
    - Rockefeller Foundation, 1959-1965 (Box 11, Folder 37)
    - Sumatra miscellaneous, 1956-1959 (Box 11, Folder 38)
    - Universities and colleges: Harvard, Michigan, California, 1958-1959 (Box 11, Folder 39)
    - The Viking Fund, 1944 (Box 11, Folder 40)
    - Wayang Kulit Purwa translation, 1957 (Box 11, Folder 41)
    - White House Dinner, 1968 (Box 11, Folder 42)
    - Yale-Southeast Asia Studies, 1961-1962 (Box 11, Folder 43)
- Series III. Research Materials
  - Wax seals (Box 5 MS)
  - Research notes (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Research material and correspondence (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Miscellaneous research (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Unused notes (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Appendix V- Art Associations (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Art Associations in Indonesia (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - 'Art in Indonesia' bibliography (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Selected readings for 'cultural roots' symposium (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Biographies (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - Dance research notes (Box 12, Folder 10)
  - Index to research files (Box 12, Folder 11)
  - Indonesia (Box 12, Folder 12)
  - Theoretical/sociological integration (Box 12, Folder 13)
  - Bangkok, 1937-1957 (Box 12, Folder 14)
  - Proposal for a dance institute, 1940 (Box 12, Folder 15)
  - Southeast Asia, 1942-1950 (Box 12, Folder 16)
  - Art- philosophical and anthropological bits, 1942-1961 (Box 12, Folder 17)
  - Indonesia, 1943-1945 (Box 12, Folder 18)
  - Research materials, 1943-1953 (Box 12, Folder 19)
  - Professional affiliations- South East Asia Institute minutes, 1945-1947 (Box 12, Folder 20)
  - Intercultural materials, 1945-1958 (Box 12, Folder 21)
  - Indonesia- Education, 1946-1949 (Box 12, Folder 22)
  - Art- theoretical and anthropological, 1946-1950 (Box 12, Folder 23)
  - China, 1946-1950 (Box 12, Folder 24)
  - Indonesia, 1946-1952 (Box 12, Folder 25)
  - Japan-U.S. policy in sea, 1946-1962 (Box 12, Folder 26)
  - Research material, 1949 (Box 12, Folder 27)
  - International theory and practice, 1949-1951 (Box 12, Folder 28)
  - Theoretical, anthropological values, 1949-1952 (Box 12, Folder 29)
  - Southeast Asia, 1949-1953 (Box 12, Folder 30)
  - "Classical Dance and Costumes of India" by Kay Ambrose, 1950 (Box 12, Folder 31)
  - Indonesia, 1950-1956 (Box 12, Folder 32)
  - Indonesian music, 1950-1960s (Box 12, Folder 33)
  - "The Role of the Chinese in Indonesia" by Robert C. Bone Jr. Includes cassette., 1951 (Box 12, Folder 34)
  - Research material, 1951-1952 (Box 12, Folder 35)
  - Cross cultural materials, 1951-1956 (Box 12, Folder 36)
  - General bibliographies, 1953-1956 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Java, article by FDK Bosch, 1954 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Travel notes, 1955-1956 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Travel notes, 1956 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Scrapbook, 1956 (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Lee Man Fong biography, 1956-1958 (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Music records lists, 1958 (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - "Indonesian Government's Policy Towards Art", by R.K. Vasil, 1958 (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - Historical Appendix, 1959 (Box 13, Folder 9)
  - Art objects list, 1964-1967 (Box 13, Folder 10)
  - Committee on Archaeological and A.M. Indonesian Council, 1966-1967 (Box 13, Folder 11)
  - Museums in Indonesia, 1967 (Box 13, Folder 12)
  - 'Kinesics' paper by R. Birdwhistell, creative dance in therapy, bender and social dance, 1967 (Box 13, Folder 13)
  - Index cards with research notes (Box 14, 15, 17)
- Series IV. Lectures and Writings
  - Archaeological service: Jakarta (Box 13, Folder 14)
  - Modern Art Bali (Bali-Java comparison) (Box 13, Folder 15)
  - Dance lectures, 1936-1942 (Box 13, Folder 16)
  - 'Dance: Form and Function' Bali Fracisca Baos School Seminar, 1941 (Box 13, Folder 17)
  - Papers, 1941-1945 (Box 13, Folder 17A)
  - Columbia University class materials, Navy School International administration, 1942 (Box 13, Folder 18)
  - Integration of Language and Culture Study, March 1944 (Box 13, Folder 19)
  - "Ardjo Travels Light", for Asia, 1944 (Box 13, Folder 20)
  - Article for Konfrontasi, February-May 1956 (Box 13, Folder 21)
  - 'A Few Contemplations on Dance', 'Two Dance Worlds'. Indonesian version, 1956 (Box 13, Folder 22)
  - Texts and lectures/articles, 1956-1957 (Box 13, Folder 23)
  - Indonesian arts and crafts, AD White Museum. Includes photographs, 1957 (Box 13, Folder 24)
  - 'Some Observations on the Visual Arts in Indonesia Today', article for Saraswati, 1957 (Box 13, Folder 25)
  - Extra curricular lectures, 1957-1963 (Box 13, Folder 26)
  - Lecture performance Wayang Kulit, 1964 (Box 13, Folder 27)
  - 'Dances in Sumatra', Cornell sea program, 1969 (Box 13, Folder 28)
  - Synopses by Holt: Ramayana, Mahabharata, Ardjuna Wiwaha, Pandji, and Damar Wulan, 1957-1962 (Box 13, Folder 29)
  - Photograph list for Art in Indonesia, 1960s (Box 13, Folder 38)
  - Cornell University Press permissions for illustrations and quotes, 1961-1969 (Box 13, Folder 30)
  - "Art in Indonesia" correspondence, re-illustrations and quotes, 1963-1965 (Box 13, Folder 31)
  - F. Siegel course lecture, Department of Anthropology, 1967 (Box 13, Folder 32)
  - "Art in Indonesia": responses, 1967-1968 (Box 13, Folder 33)
  - "Art in Indonesia" second edition materials for corrections, 1967-1968 (Box 13, Folder 34)
  - In memoriam- Robert Heine-Geldern. For Indonesia., 1968 (Box 13, Folder 35)
  - The Story of Tchoopak and Granting, text and art (Box 13, Folder 36)
- Series V. Cornell Indonesian Arts Project
  - Dance, 1933-1955 (Box 19, Folder 1)
  - Programs, Wajung/Lakons (Box 19, Folder 2)
  - Biographical information, 1949 (Box 19, Folder 4)
  - ICA report on visual aids, 1950s (Box 19, Folder 5)
  - Batik information and photographs, 1950s-1960s (Box 19, Folder 6)
  - Asri, Jojga, 1950-1955 (Box 19, Folder 7)
  - Conferences, NGWS, 1950-1957 (Box 19, Folder 8)
  - Governmental budgets and policies, 1951-1956 (Box 19, Folder 9)
  - Sticusa, 1952-1955 (Box 19, Folder 10)
  - "Art Today," arts and crafts, 1951-1958 (Box 19, Folder 11)
  - Cultural change, 1952-1956 (Box 19, Folder 12)
  - Drafts of project, 1954 (Box 19, Folder 13)
  - "Fine Arts" Bandung, 1954-1955 (Box 19, Folder 14)
  - Sumatra art associations, 1954-1955 (Box 19, Folder 15)
  - Travel arrangements (field), 1954-1955 (Box 19, Folder 16)
  - Financial basic budget, 1954-1958 (Box 19, Folder 17)
  - Symbols, 1955 (Box 19, Folder 18)
  - Sukarno, 1955 (Box 19, Folder 19)
  - Painting Badan Kontak, 1955 (Box 19, Folder 20)
  - Dance, 1955 (Box 19, Folder 21)
  - Solo art associations, 1955-1956 (Box 19, Folder 22)
  - Art criticism and writings on, 1955-1956 (Box 19, Folder 23)
  - Dance programs, 1955-1956 (Box 19, Folder 24)
  - Painting- catalogues I, 1955-1956 (Box 19, Folder 25)
  - Painting-catalogues II, 1955-1960 (Box 19, Folder 26)
  - Catalgoues III- Pelukis Rakjat, 1955-1958 (Box 19, Folder 27)
  - AMIATI, 1955-1967 (Box 19, Folder 28)
  - Jakarta associations, 1956 (Box 19, Folder 29)
  - Art associations, Jogja, 1956 (Box 19, Folder 30)
  - Jogja-Gadjah Mada, 1956 (Box 19, Folder 31)
  - Monuments, Musea, 1956 (Box 19, Folder 32)
  - Sumatra art education, 1956 (Box 19, Folder 33)
  - Sumatra-Itineraries, addresses, contacts, events, 1956 (Box 19, Folder 34)
  - Yanto Painting, 1956 (Box 19, Folder 35)
  - Badan Musjawarat Kebudajaan Nasional (BMKN) almanac, 1956-1957 (Box 19, Folder 36)
  - Programs-drama, 1956-1959 (Box 19, Folder 37)
  - Bali Art, 1956-1964 (Box 19, Folder 38)
  - Post 1957 developments (Box 19, Folder 39)
  - LKN cultural organizations, 1959 (Box 19, Folder 40)
  - Lekra, 1956 (Box 19, Folder 41)
  - Dance-KBW, 1959-1960 (Box 19, Folder 42)
  - Bandung Painters, 1962 (Box 19, Folder 43)
  - Affandi-biographical, 1962-1963 (Box 19, Folder 44)
  - Painting-biographical, 1967-1968 (Box 19, Folder 45)
  - Collectors of Modern Art, 1969 (Box 19, Folder 46)
- Series VI. Claire Holt Memorial Collection
  - Audio tape: dedication of the Claire Holt memorial, inauguration ceremony at Lembaga. Two copies. Part I., August 6, 1987; TR-7988 (Box 13, Folder 39)
  - Audio tape: dedication of the Claire Holt memorial, inauguration ceremony at Lembaga. Two copies. Part II., August 6, 1970; TR-7989 (Box 13, Folder 40)
  - Photographs and typescript of Claire Holt memorial inauguration ceremony, August 6, 1970 (Box 13, Folder 41)